good morning david
um this is really in the whole series of
interviews that i've been doing in this
voices of the regeneration probably one
of the calls that i
to some extent was most nervous about
and but also feel the most honored that
i get a chance to
um speak to you it's it's really um
a privilege to to be able to have this
conversation with you so thank you so
much for making time well thank you
that's very uh very kind of you indeed
so i i've been um
i'm originally a biologist myself and um
i studied biology at edinburgh
university
and somehow got a little bit
disheartened with the reductionist focus
that um
behavioral biology had at the time of i
studied zoology wanted to become a
marine
biologist and even in my early years
working
with bernie liberth in california on
elephant sea of populations
um i'm sure you're aware of some of his
work
this is the early days of sociobiology i
i
basically realized that
there was something about the limitation
of the viewpoint of
conventional research science these days
that that didn't quite
fit me as a box to spend my life in but
at the
the same time i i've always maintained
that fascination for basically i studied
biology because i wanted to understand
how life works
and how the process of life in geneva
genevanese's works
uh words creates conditions conducive to
life
and partially got disheartened with
biology
because the the mystique of the
naturalist like humboldt or darwin
um was somehow taken away by
the p-value of statistical significance
and
um and only quantifiable data being
the data that that could be part of the
discourse
um i just feel like like saying that to
to
situate your self um or myself within
the context of our conversation because
then many years later i
did a masters in holistic science and i
had the great fortune of
um doing like studying with
professor brian goodwin who um has a
very
much complexity theory informed take on
on evolution
and um just
more recently in 2016 i published this
book designing regenerative cultures
which
just after the publication a friend of
mine
put me in touch with a um young man
called joe brewer
who i hadn't known of before um but
because my
my book had the title designing
regenerative cultures
this friend of mine david hodgson said
you need to talk to joe brewer about
um culture design and that's really when
i first
started to to hear because he spoke very
highly of you and he was working with
you at the evolution institute at the
time i believe
and um and that's when i started looking
into your work
and i i feel like i need to apologize
that i don't mention your work in my
book i
i just was aware of it afterwards
um but it's very much aligned with one
of the common themes in my book and
like i understand that what you've
developed over the last 30 years
is a scientifically rigorous
theory and argument based on the
darwinian
[Music]
evolutionary theory that
cooperation altruism and behavior
in benefit of the larger hole is
actually
something something that um evolution
selects for
and that speaks to me so strongly the
the whole notion that life
isn't like we can see life as
individuals competing with each other or
species competing with each other
but that's just one slice of one way of
seeing
this planetary process that um
has over the course of 3.8 billion years
made this planet more diverse more
abundant more bioproductive
more capable of supporting more complex
and diverse life forms and um
normally i start this series with with
an invitation to
the person to introduce themselves
rather than read out the long bio so i i
would
love for you to to basically tell your
story a bit
how did you um get into this work
and how has it been
in the orthodox evolutionary field
to that that somehow seems to be very
enamored with the the the dogma of
competition drives everything
um to be a voice to say no actually
that's not quite how darwinian evolution
works
sure well uh yeah i'll do it in a way
that i think which connects to some very
general themes and goes way beyond my
own personal
uh trajectory i think it's almost
inevitable it happens again and again
with
the study of any topic when you look at
it historically
is that it begins with an appreciation
of complexity um
because everything is so complex and
when you first encounter it and
especially before you
try to study it formally and you're
thinking about it in words you're
describing it in words
and it's easy to uh emphasize the rich
tapestry of life
the great complexity of economic systems
of course physical systems and so on
because after all
they are indubitably complex
but once you try to go beyond verbal
descriptions and to study any topic
more formally for example using
mathematics
then inevitably simplification is
required
i i'm starting my career as a
mathematical
modeler anyone who actually bills
mathematical models knows how many
simplifying assumptions you have to make
just to grant through the math so
this is then i think a reductionistic
phase that almost all topics
go through and there's great insights
that come from that you build your
simple models they do
result in insights but then ultimately
they reveal their limitations
and it's at this point then you slowly
begin to
appreciate complexity again it builds
back
to the study of complexity
and we really have to remember that
the study of complex systems
requires computational methods
because analytical math is inherently
limited i like to refer to the
the the distinction between the two-body
problem and the three-body problem
in physics so you know the two-body
problem two celestial bodies
um rotating around each other in space
you can predict that with mathematical
equations no problem
three bodies rotating around each other
in space
that's like enormously complex and even
though you might be able to do it
if you alter the initial conditions even
infinitesimally then the trajectories
will all be
different that's what we know is
sensitive dependence on initial
conditions so without basically clients
and computing
then there was no way to go beyond
analytical
mathematical models and
widespread computing wasn't available
until the closing decades of the 20th
century
so we didn't even have the tools to
to study scientifically study complex
systems of any sort
before those availability of those
um of those uh tools and so that's why i
think that when you encountered this and
basically um became a biologist during
its reductionistic phase
then and you found it lacking
then um that might be for some of the
the reasons now another thing that
happened in evolutionary biology
was that even though darwin thought that
his theory applied to all aspects of
humanity in addition to
the natural world the study of evolution
became highly gene-centric
yeah for most of the 20th century and
and had
nothing whatsoever to say about culture
nothing whatsoever to say about
culture especially or much of anything
to do with humans and so
the study of humans was ceded to other
disciplines the human related
disciplines which
bodies but without reference to
evolutionary theory
very often in perceived opposition to
evolutionary
theory and so you have this archipelago
of knowledge which i
frequently uh uh
like to to reflect on many islands of
thought with little communication
among islands and you know the great
the triumph and the magnificence of
evolutionary theory is its unifying
uh capacity and it has unified the
biological sciences but that unification
has not yet taken place
for the human related sciences that's
what's in
progress so that's why my book is titled
this view of life
completing the darwinian
darwinian uh a revolution so it's only
within the
the last literally within the last 30
years starting in the closing decades of
the 20th century
that evolutionists evolutionary thinkers
went back to basics
and they said evolution or darwinian
evolution
is any process that combines the three
ingredients
of variation selection and replication
any process
genetic evolution is one such process
but there are
others there are others in fact there's
many
of them and so this broadening out
of evolutionary theory now encompassing
at last
darwin's vision of encompassing
all things human is what's on offer
uh today it's i think it's really a
grand synthesis we
we look back on the 20th century we say
oh what a period of synthesis
well that's where we are now with
respect to
human related knowledge and as you can
see i have a great passion for
for uh
um i mean let me just like because i
mentioned brian goodwin earlier
brian taught me also related to the
three-body problem
he had this slightly oversimplified
definition of a complex
system saying any system that has more
than three interacting
variables is a complex system and then
then he would often say
um and once you're in that realm their
behavior
is fundamentally unpredictable
uncontrollable beyond the very limited
temporal spatial scale you can wrestle
some predictability from
from the system if you define the
boundaries both temporally and specially
to say in a limited way but if you
really look at it in its context
it's fundamentally unpredictable and
controllable and his
conclusion and that's an
an anxiomatic change in science is that
he he was
sort of speaking to the fact that
throughout the scientific revolution and
for the beginning years of
of of science and its diversification
into all these silos and disciplines
it was all about increasing prediction
control and manipulation of nature it
was the sort of binding nature and
all these quotes that we know from from
um
bacon and so on and he said that
what complexity science is offering
is a fun fundamental reframe towards
appropriate participation that since we
cannot predict and control
we actually have to understand how do we
best
fit in to this nested wholeness of
life's
ongoing exploration of novelty um
does that resonate with with your
perspective or do you think that now we
have
the ai to actually wrestle
predictability
um from life
or complex systems well it does resonate
but in a very complicated way
and uh to get back to the three-body
problem the most wonderful demonstration
of that for me
and it's in part an artistic
demonstration is
the jointed pendulum and i didn't
know anything about jointed pendulums
until i was just poking around the
internet
um but you know a pendulum that's just a
single stick that that uh that you know
swings back and forth
that's totally predictable but all you
need to do is to take that very same
pendulum
and give it a couple of joints so now
now that you know they can
and then uh and then trace this
trajectory like just imagine that this
is going back
and forth and a little pen is tracing it
as trajectory
it traces the most beautiful
artwork as these joints you know the
different arms of the
you know are swinging around each other
and stuff like that and of course every
time you set it in motion it traces a
different picture
so just going from a single
arm pendulum to a jointed pendulum with
two or three arms
um undergoes that transition from
something that is very simple and
predictable
to something that is that is just
infinite and it's uh
infinite it's in its variety and yet at
the same time
um complex systems
have there's plenty of pattern and
complex
systems you know there's multiple basins
of attraction
um uh systems come to rest on
on uh one of them um so
we you know it demonstrates that kind of
local
equilibrium and here's a very important
point
that living complex systems
because they are sculpted by natural
selection
are perfectly predictable we know we
we can predict i mean to a impressive
degree
the way animals are how they adapt and
so on and so forth so
uh complex systems needed to be divided
into two
categories one is complex systems in
general of course that's the
that's the most general category then
there's non-living complex systems and
there's living
complex systems and living complex
systems because they have been sculpted
by
by natural selection have
a great deal of of uh a predictor look
at our anatomy and physiology
you know uh so all kinds of credibility
that there must be if
if any entity is going to be well
adapted to survive and reproduce
in its uh in its environment and i think
a lot about this because
and i'd be interested to know your
experience you've already kind of
alluded to this
aversion to an overly mechanistic
uh conception of how we can engineer
things you know as if it's some great
machine that we can build
and run and there seems to be something
wrong about that
to many to many people and
as an alternative they often people
turn to various kinds of organic
metaphors such as an ecosystem
or a garden and a gardening cultivating
a garden
is perceived to be importantly different
than
than um than a machine and the machine
the garden metaphor is
seen to be importantly different than
the machine metaphor
now that fascinates me because i
actually
i love the garden and i know how much
work is required to plan
and maintain a garden so much work
so much weeding so much cultivation so
much
attention to the plants to
figure out what makes them um
and often there's it's filled with
uncertainties if something's not
going well in your garden well you don't
actually know exactly what it is so you
have to try
this and that but nevertheless the idea
that
gardens don't need to be
that the word manage is wrong for a
garden
i don't get that i mean there's an
intense form of management that's
that's taken place um so and i i puzzle
over that
that uh so with our systems
with our social systems our economic
systems our interactions with nature
all my heavens i mean we have to do some
form of management
it's going to be the gardening form it's
actually called adaptive management
that's probably a term that's
that's familiar to you what is adaptive
management basically
you know you're working with a complex
system
you try stuff out to the best of your
knowledge and you assess to see if it's
working
and if it's not you try something else
that's what adaptive
management is and this what we need to
do so
but it's a form of management so what do
you think of all that well i i
completely agree i think that
there is a there's a nuance difference
and just in in in the framing of it that
i think that there's too much of a
tendency that we believe that
with improved science and improved
technology
um we can
really control and and the uncertainty
factor
is still present and so while it's not
saying that we can't
control a lot and like brian would call
it
um setting the enabling constraints
for positive emergence so so something
in the system is going to emerge in
emergence
has become a bit of a buzzword that is
very flatly used by a lot of people
but because emergence can be good or bad
in the system depending on what values
you
you put in what you assume to be good or
bad in the system
um but it's
the the notion of really understanding
that
that there is always something that is
beyond
our knowing that um the the complexity
of the nested system
within which our planet sits is such
that we can always be thrown a curveball
and and that just sets us a um
a base attitude of humility and i i
quite like this notion of approp
participation it doesn't mean like it it
can be very much in the sense of a
gardener
and setting the enabling constraints
like i find it very dangerous
right now in this conversation around we
need to move from
um ego to eco or more and more people
criticizing all of humanity and and our
destructive actions on the planet
um trying to create a picture of
re-wilding
as places devoid of human beings and
for me that would be bowing out of our
responsibility that as
agents in this life as a planetary
process system
we have interfered with it on every
continent in every ecosystem on the
planet by now
and therefore we have the role of
becoming conscious participants
in evolution and humble
keystone species that that try to
increase
bioproductivity and diversity and and
systemic resilience at multiple levels
of scale
to the best of our abilities but from
this base attitude of
acknowledging uncertainty and
uncontrollability because that
that will just to my mind
set the frame under which we then avoid
um
large geoengineering processes where we
believe we
like arrogantly believe that if we just
throw x tons of
of ferrous oxide in the oceans we will
cause algal blooms and that will then
draw down co2 for me it's that hubris
of playing with a system that is too
complex to control
um at that scale that we need to
work against yeah so so
uh i agree one of the lessons of complex
systems is uh humility
because because we are an immersed
income we are complex systems and we're
in
who live within complex systems and by
definition
complex systems are
filled with unforeseen uh
consequences so we'll never have enough
knowledge really
to know the consequences of our actions
that's why we must always be
humble and we must um and we must try
things out and then
assess what works and then replicate
those
and that's sensitive to context so even
if we figure out something that works
here it doesn't won't necessarily work
there without
tweaking that's how that's how humble we
have to be so humility
is absolutely uh called for there's
point one i think that's
everyone should should um agree upon
that that's revealed i think with the
pandemic where
where i mean some of the really bad
ideas like herd immunity
were the result of models and scientists
i mean the models were telling them that
that would be well turned out not to be
the case
so their head it's like the weather i
think the weather
forecasting is a great metaphor for
what has to take place with all complex
systems the weather is a complex
physical system it's so complex that
with all of the effort that we put onto
it
we still can't predict the fucking
weather can we yeah
not even not even a few days
ahead of time and so we have an arsenal
of models we have
we're gathering data at an incredible
refreshing rate you know the data again
and again
and then we test our models and and
that's how how we do it well actually
all complex systems need to be on that
uh need to be
much uh much like that but i i want to
say some more about natural
systems it's so very important and all
of this is paradigmatic
which means that um
if you if you don't get it you're in
some other paradigm then you know it's
going to
it's going to shape your worldview and
if you get it
the new paradigm then is going to
reshape your worldview in both cases it
can be highly intuitive and
common sensible but work is required to
go from one paradigm to
to uh another and there's a very strong
tendency to uh
think that nature left to itself
strike some form of harmonious balance
and that's what i mean the whole
wilderness
ethic that you just talked about is just
you know get humans out of there
and then nature will will we
will revert to its its
its state which is some kind of benign
state that's actually a pre-darwinian
notion that's a christian
notion and the christian worldview is
that
the world was created by god and is
therefore well ordered from top to
bottom
darwin's theory of evolution tells us
something
very different evolution does not make
everything
nice evolution results in
all kinds of outcomes that are horrible
from a human
standpoint exploitative predatory
competitive
so there's all kinds of of um
single species social groups and and uh
multi-species communities that would be
just despotic in human terms
the very last kind of society that we
would
want to live in i have a number of
podcasts on this with biologists
including a primatologist named joan
silk who should
know i mean just imagine living in a
society was just
basically donald trump won and
everyone's like him now
dominating individuals what would it be
like if so a male comes into your group
kills your children
and then insists that you mate with him
to have
his children and then some other bastard
comes and kills them and
you have to repeat the cycle but you
have to put up with it because if you
were to leave then you'd be on your own
and you'd be certainly
that would be certain death think about
that
think about the most abusive
relationship that you could imagine
the kind of relationship where just
someone comes to kill you if you
leave but you have to put up with it
think about that
that being just the way entire species
have been shaped
and it's just never going to be
different because that's the
the uh the way the selection pressures
have
have just uh molded the mold of the
species and so community ecologists
in modern day use the word regime
when they talk about multi-species
communities they talk about biological
regimes
and i think that's such a great word
because we have an intuition
about human political regimes um
a regime is somewhat stable otherwise
you'd never call it a regime
right so the word regime conveys a
degree of stability but it does not
convey
how good or bad that regime is a regime
can be an enlightened regime
it can be a despotic regime
the word eugene is agnostic as a but the
quality
of the regime for those who those who
live
within it and so it turns out that
natural regimes biological
regimes are like human regimes they do
not strike
harmonious balance left to themselves
uh necessarily and so the hard lesson
of evolution is is that there is
no functional organization without a
process
of selection the reason that individuals
are functionally organized that we
function so well
as collections of trillions of cells
is because of natural operating at the
individual
level the reason that social insect
colonies function as well as they
do is because of a process of natural
selection operating at the colony
level if human groups function as
cooperative units it's thanks only to a
process of selection
at that level at that level if nations
function well
it's only because of a process of of
selection at that level and if the
planet is going to function well it will
only be thanks to a process of selection
in this case
policy selection in which we base our
actions
on the good of the planet the whole
concept of laissez faire
that basically that lower level entities
can pursue their interests and that
works out for the common good
it's just profoundly untrue it's untrue
in economics it's untrue in biology
and so uh so now we're getting into the
concept of multi-level selection
just briefly on on that the
what i understand you
are saying in with multi-level selection
is is that
um well i mean there's the the famous um
phrase that you get
probably quoted at um more often than
you would like to
re-hear that phrase of um
selfish individuals were will out
compete
within groups um and uh
altruistic groups will out-compete
selfish groups and all else's
um what was that
i can't remember the exact line and the
mantra this is the
the concluding sentence of my article
with the other wilson edward ovals and
selfishness beats altruism within groups
altruistic groups
be selfish group everything else is
commentary yeah that that's the one
thank you
and ultimately what i understand is that
um like in in my framing
around regeneration working with with
friends like for example
bill sharp um has this framing of saying
that all
life exists within the tension of
being for oneself and being as part of a
larger whole
and that speaks to to this multi-level
nestedness that um on the one hand we
have these
individual benefits from acting in a
certain way but we're also dependent
on the larger group also multi-species
groups
maintaining the viability of the system
that we are actually drawing viability
from
and and what i've understood you
you're saying is that the difficulty of
making these jumps in evolution to
taking care of the larger system is that
that actually
is often not as
advantageous for individuals or groups
or nations within that next
higher um level
is that correct it is correct and
it's often something that often is and
can be stated as a form of self-interest
that you can say
you know in order for you to benefit you
must benefit
the social group that you're in or the
ecology that you're
that you're in and so the the most
enlightened form of self-interest is to
work on behalf
with others on behalf of these larger
entities
um the problem with that way of thinking
uh is that
it basically it it fails to appreciate
that natural selection is based on
relative
uh fitness not absolute fitness it's not
a matter of like
you should do a because that's better
for you than if you do b
that's a comparison of your fitness and
under the assumption that people will be
motivated to maximize their absolute
fitness but evolution is always based on
who's doing better than who and
um it's uh it's relative and the the
best example of that is cancer
cancer cells proliferate at the expense
of normal cells
within the body the normal cells of the
normal cells of the solid citizen
cells they're the ones that are acting
on their enlightened self-interest you
you might say participating with other
cells to keep the whole
organisms alive cancer cells
don't do that they're they're the
short-sighted self
selfish selfish kind and they're
ultimately going to kill themselves
each and every time they bring about
their own
demise and so but nevertheless cancer
cells
it's just they proliferate faster than
the normal cells that's
it that's it and so they increase in
frequency
every time there's a mutation that
causes a cancer
a cell to proliferate at the expense of
the it just
happens and then with subsequent
mutations it happens more
then they learn then they evolve to
disperse as metastasis that's just
natural selection taking place within
the body based on a relative fitness it
has no foresight
it has no foresight and so if you get
someone if you pair
the enlightened self-interest person
who says oh i'll be better off we'll all
be better off if we work together
that's in our enlightened self-interest
and then if you put in a short-sighted
selfish person who exploits that
well they'll win it's i mean it's
relative fitness my friend
and so the selfish individual
even if it's not intentional will
proliferate benefit at
the expense of the election there's no
foresight
there's no foresight it just happens and
so if you have nations trying to
grow their economy and that ends up
overheating
the earth and then we look at that see
how can you do that when you
when when it's bad for assault well it
just happens
but how would you consequences and so so
this is the
this is to be harder in terms of in
terms of uh
formulating our policy not just
appealing to
to uh enlighten self-interest we have to
create
social organizations which are
protective
against various forms of disruptive
lower level
activities they have to be constructed
in order to prevent
disruptive forms of cheating and free
riding and
and all of these things which are
beneficial at a small scale but
disruptive at a
at a larger scale if you're not
protecting yourselves against them they
will
happen their various forms of cancer
will take place
so how would you in terms of the the
urgency of the
human predicament that we're currently
faced with um with regard to
um the jury is still out how many years
or decades we still got left but
and somewhere between less than a decade
and maybe two or three decades
to avoid um cataclysmic climate change
um just hitting um runaway feedbacks
mechanisms in the climate system that
that even if we then
all pulled together and did the right
thing um we'd have to admit to ourselves
that it's too late
um i mean obviously the work that you've
done with pro social
uh seems to suggest that there is a
chance that
that we could rearrange our activity in
such a way that um
we incentivize pro-social behavior
um that we set policies that are for
the benefit of of uh
life as a planetary process and
therefore for the longevity of humanity
um
like what you said earlier i just wanted
to double check
check that i i heard you right because
in my perspective
in order to rematch in terms of the the
whole
redesign of the human impact on the
planet
rematch our activities in the way we
meet our needs
through the biophysical realities of
ecosystems
and the biosphere we actually need to
relocalize some of our patterns quite
drastically
um because as you also said earlier it's
all about context so one solution that
fits in one place might not fit in
another place
we need to match our solutions to the
the diversity
of conditions of each ecosystem in each
culture
um that for me suggests and there's a
lot of people
um working on this indeed from different
angles the planetary health
alliance from from a more population
health perspective
or the capital institute's um
regenerative communities network and
and bioregional initiatives around
economic regeneration
and it suggests a bioregional approach
an approach where we where we fit human
activities back to
um the unique conditions of each
bioregion or ecosystem
that they live in but it requires global
collaboration between bioregions to do
this process
um do you think that that runs against
all that you
you see from the study of evolution as a
process or
can can you fit because
to my mind eleanor uh austrian's
work on on the commons is critical
on how to enable people
at a bioregional scale to wisely manage
the resources within that bioregion in
such a way that they don't
impinge on bioregions elsewhere and
actually enable bioregions elsewhere to
do the same thing
is it does that resonate with your work
or not sure i think what you just
outlined for my regional approach
is exactly what we need to be reaching
for so there's our
amiga point basically there's our um
our goal it's a kind of a multi-level
governance
um that is uh has the global good in
mind but also
is uh and that's reflected in all the
intermediate layers of organization the
bio regions
uh the cities um and all the way down to
lower levels of governments especially
the level of smaller groups which we
will uh we'll get to buster by all means
that is
our target of selection you might uh you
might
uh you might say and so it's a matter of
how we actually get there how do we
actually
achieve that that vision
and before i comment on that i i just
wanted to point out as others have i'm
no expert on this topic
that uh irreversible climate change and
kind of leading to a
cataclysmic tipping point that's true
for humans but it's not true for the
rest of life on earth
oh yeah absolutely i've heard it said
that you know the earth could be six
degrees celsius warmer
that'd be just fine for the original
life
on earth just bad for us real bad for us
so so i think that um we need to
keep that in mind so
so now back to the question is how we
actually achieve this vision that you
articulated very well and i really want
to stress
that is our goal that's exactly what we
want to do but how do we go about
uh doing it and
austria herself wrote about this in one
of the last papers that she wrote
on on uh
multi-level uh governance she called it
polycentric
uh governance and i was privileged as i
think you know to work with
her for three years prior to her death
and what we did was we generalized her
work
from a evolutionary uh perspective
and we showed that that
what she derived for a certain kind of
group common pool resource
groups is basically applies to all
groups whose members are trying to
cooperate with each other you can think
of cooperation
as itself a common pool uh
a resource so there's a set of
principles that can be
i mean it's really amazing when you when
you think of it just
think carefully absorb this i ask your
listeners to absorb this there is a
simple set of principles
that applies to all kinds of groups
no matter what they are trying to do and
those same principles are scale
independent
they can govern relations among groups
in addition to relations within groups
wouldn't you want to know about those
principles i would so
so um that's what's uh
on offer and
when i when i read those um strong group
identity and
understanding of purpose one fair
distribution of costs and benefits two
fair and inclusive decision makings
three
monitoring agreed upon behaviors four
graduated sanctions for misbehaviors
five
fast and fair conflict resolution six
authority to self-govern seven
appropriate
relationships with other groups eight
it's it sounds very similar it sounds
neat but you also in other works that
i've been
listening to videos and you looked at
eco villages and intentional communities
and
we we would have a lot of places to go
here but in my experience from having
worked with eco villages
and having worked with with the the
people willing to work together and
manage common
pool resources it's actually not that
easy to create
um for example uh
mechanisms for for fast and fair
conflict resolution
um so so in in the detail of how to
apply these
eight principles there's a lot of uh
hard work to be done or have you
seen them applied gracefully in all
sorts of
um contexts without bumping into
human complexity yeah so there's uh
uh so much to say here uh and it's
paradoxical uh so let's spend some
time on this first it's very important
to remind ourselves
exactly what ostrom showed for common
pool
resource rivers which she studied around
the world
what she showed was that they varied
in their ability to avoid the tragedy of
the commons not all of them were able to
manage their common pool
resources only some there was your
bell-shaped curve
only some were able to manage their
commons
most were in between and then there were
the disasters on the other end of the
bell curve so common pool resource
groups that she started buried
from the best of the worst the best
employed these core design
principles and that's what made them
work so
well now generalizing the core design
principles means
that when we examine any other kind of
groups
schools businesses neighborhoods
families nonprofits any
cooperative endeavor you'll find
your bell-shaped curve some will work
spectacularly well
most will be in the middle and then
you'll have your
basket cases on the other end
of the bell curve that goes for
intentional communities
as well as any other kind of group and
we've done research
on on this to basically back up that
back up that claim as it turns out the
research that we've done
on intentional communities shows it as a
group they perform pretty well
uh you know the bell shape is kind of
shifted
in the good direction for that
particular kind of
uh for that particular kind of group but
even so
all kind of of a variation so it is not
the case that groups just all groups
just spontaneously
uh implement the core design principles
not at all
that's why work is required but actually
that's your first task
your first task is to work at the scale
of
of small functionally
oriented groups and i'll say more about
that
in a minute and then of course we need
to work at still larger skills
but if the if the small groups aren't
working well then larger society is not
going to work well
that's for sure so one one project and
it's quite a
doable project this is something that
anybody who's listening to this
can do if they're already
in groups that are meaningful to them
then they can learn about this approach
and they can make their groups function
better if they're not in a group
well find one or to make one
work in groups and i'll say more about
that
in a minute so there's something that's
just that's an incredibly important
insight to be able to
to make about about working at the level
of small groups which everyone can do
and then of course those groups have to
be coordinated that's when we go up in
the scale
i the the
the suspicion i have
that in that data set that ostrom
studied
one of the common patterns for the ones
that were the ones that failed
because not all of these eight
principles the authority to self-govern
is one of those slightly
slippery ones because that's not
entirely within the
um jurisdiction of the group itself and
and very often what i think is the most
destructive factor of a group of people
trying to manage a common pool
resource is if they're embedded in a
system that is actually stacked against
them and and i find this over and over
now when
when i have conversations with people
around could we cr
could i turn my company over to being a
regenerative company
and if we're if we're still in the zero
sum um
competitive environment of the current
economic playing field
it is very difficult for companies to
really
become regenerative because the the
playing field is stacked against them
and
my sense is that some of the the
these common pool resource management
attempts
failed because of that they're nested in
within a larger system that also
influenced their success and failure
the core design principles are a little
bit like the organs of your body
um everyone is native
you move a single one and you die so and
it's not quite that bad but
but um but there is a sense in which um
a group can fail for um
for lack of uh any one of the cortisone
principles and the one that you've
pointed out
local autonomy the groups just don't
have the elbow room
or they're operating in a in a larger
environment that's stacked against them
that is indeed huge make no mistake
and you and i have both done a lot of
reading um
about that lately i've been rating about
platform cooperatives which i'll bet you
know about
as well the idea that basically you know
things like airbnb
and uber and and lyft the gig economy
you know that those could actually work
pretty well if they weren't so
exploitative you know if they weren't so
locked into the capitalist
model and come to try to create a a
cooperative platform and you realize
that there's all kind of legislation
that stacked
against it that makes it hard not not
easy and whenever i talk to people
all the time about this sort of thing
and they talk about their institutional
environment
mostly as the institutional environment
is
is a problem is is is basically
holding them back that was my own
experience when i tried to
the first project that i tried to start
in my uh my
hometown of hometown of binghamton
nevertheless
there's many internal uh problems
how in how many groups is there an
unequal
allocation of costs and benefits in
other words some people do most of the
work some members of the group do most
of the work
other members get the benefit and how
many groups especially in businesses
is decision making not fair and
equitable some people in within the
group don't have
uh aren't part of the decision-making
uh uh process and how many groups is it
the case that
basically there's no monitoring of
agreed-upon behavior goes on and on
so so uh every group needs to do an
assessment
and then they need to improve the things
that they're in a position to improve
upon
and if there's things that they can't
control
then those are obstacles that we need to
move around
and that actually introduces another
element of pro-social which is just as
important as the core
design principles which is the capacity
to be
adaptable flexible and
evolvable so just because you have an
aspiration
doesn't mean you can achieve it i like
to say that
every year we make our new year's
resolutions and every year we fail to
keep them
so so and the same is true for groups a
group could decide to
implement the core design principles
better that doesn't mean that they can
do it anymore that we can achieve our
new year's resolutions and so there's a
whole process that's required
in order to become unstuck unstuck
and to move towards our valued
goals and here this and these these
techniques come from
like therapy mindfulness based
therapy which turns out to be highly
evidence-based i mean there's
techniques that work that can make you
more flexible
as an individual and as an organization
these are teachable skills
and that's great to know and this is
what what you've been
setting up with the pro social platform
prosocial.world to to enable people to
train
to work with groups organizations
businesses cooperatives
units this is our grand this is our
grand platform that we're trying to
create and i invite
all of your listeners to to uh
uh uh check it out basically we're
trying to create the architecture
for working at all scales starting with
groups
to make them more flexible and to
uh in evolutionary terms to accomplish a
major
transition so that
these internal uh divisive interactions
disruptive interactions the group
becomes protected against them
and that they could operate as an
organism basically as a group level
as a group level of organism i mean i i
sense
talking to you that there is such an
powerful synergy between your work
and this impulse of working
regeneratively because
regeneratively might be a bit obscure as
a word but it is basically working from
a developmental and evolutionary
perspective
understanding that the idea that there
is some sort of
regenerative culture or sustainable
future or
sustainable human settlement that that
we can just design on a drawing board
and then
implement everywhere the same kind of
pattern
and once we arrived there we can happily
live
ever after is of course completely
limited
and and the the idea of working
regeneratively is working
with people in place to um
build the capacity of these people to
both individually and as a group
contribute the uniqueness of
what each individual or the group
carries as a unique essence and
contribution to the evolutionary process
and to be able to express that within
the context of the larger hole that they
they're sitting in and and it's it's
literally building
the flexibility and adaptability into
the the groups the social system
that we can continue to evolve and adapt
to changing to a changing environment
but we do so
with the understanding that
at every level the maximum potential can
only be expressed
through the appropriate fit into the
larger
nested level and in in a way that it's
in my language from my academic like my
phd wasn't designed for human and
planetary health
and i borrowed aaron antonovsky's um
notion of salutogenic approach to health
um to to coin this idea of salutogenic
design and that that marries very well
with with
the sort of regenexx cis lineage
what do we what do you contribute to the
next wider
nested hole and how do you maintain
maintain the the
the capacity to evolve of the wider
system
that your system is embedded in so it
feels
um very much aligned and
and i'd love you to say a little bit
more about these processes like if if
people are listening and saying i want
to work with my group my
bioregional um regeneration activity
initiative or my my eco village
community um
on applying these principles where would
they go and and
how would they get involved with with um
experimenting
yeah well
so happy that you raised this set of
a set of issues and there is alignment a
huge degree
of um alignment so much that
we have to ask the question you know
what's the added value
that if you're in this particular
movement have more or less converged
upon
the the same vision then
um then um
what's the added value you know maybe
you know i've just reinvented the wheel
talking about the same stuff and in in
in
in different ways and now i think that's
not the case and i'll now explain
why that is there's so many convergences
of this
of this sort that's one interesting
point to
uh make oh i mean it's almost like
i mean it's almost not an exaggeration
you see
every day i come upon people
and organizations it's more or less
converged upon the same
awareness and best practices sociocracy
is one that i could
i could uh holocracy is
as another i've really made a hobby of
of looking in the management
literature business corporations often
have
uh some of them have come upon ingenious
ways to evolve their
their uh futures typically it's you know
the
these the objectives of the of the
business which might be a corporate
objectives but nevertheless they've
developed magnificent procedures
basically continuing improvement
procedures variation
selection procedures in order to get
better and better and better
and what their what they're trying to
uh trying to do if they could turn that
genius to the global good
then that would be just you know
if you look at any one of these
and you ask what is its narrative
what is its religion what is its
justification how does it explain itself
what is its rationale how does it
replicate
um what you find is is that there's a
lot of
localism in that these tend to arise in
a particular time
and place and they're described with a
certain vocabulary
they spread to a degree uh based on
their
success but then they come up against
limits beyond which they are truly
unknown
truly unknown no one's ever heard of
them so you know they're
famous and well known within their
sphere
but then they come up against limits
and did i say that decades was required
for them to spread to the limits that
they
did the degree that they that they uh
that they do and this is so much this is
why i'm so happy
you know that you are too to actually
have a biological
background because isn't that the way
species are species originate in a
certain time and place they spread on
the basis of their success and then they
come up against them
it's their geographical geographical
distribution and so what's needed to go
beyond this kind of
uh limited
success is to be able to formulate
it in more general terms so that they so
that we could really see
what are the principles that can be
applied to
any through any context any
scale that general level of description
based basically on on foundational
theory and you can't get more
foundational than complex systems theory
and evolutionary
theory when you state it that way and if
you actually bring in to bear
state-of-the-art assessment and and
and and things like that then
uh then you've got something that's
capable of spreading worldwide
and fast and basically providing a
common language
that all of these different uh
traditions
that have indeed happened upon the same
thing and have all kind of wisdom based
on experience
that um to to draw upon
can can actually merge and combine
in a way that was not taking place
before you basically you transcended
this archipelago
structure of knowledge and knowledge and
uh
and practice so that's what we're doing
and uh
and it's so exciting to see it happening
in a collaborative
uh collaborative and not a competitive
uh
spirit that um
and then i'd want to spread that still
further
in in your area basically
of regenerative design would be we will
learn from you
and uh and we can uh
add value in terms of the practices what
we're what we're
what we're attempting to uh what we're
attempting to do
absolutely i mean i came across just
doing the research for our
conversation i came across this report
that the revolution institute did for
the b corporations in 2016 i think it
was entitled doing well by doing good
and in it you summarize these these
three very basic
um
kind of behavioral rules for effective
groups
i think it was group members must
appropriate coordinate their actions
they must avoid disruptive self-serving
behaviors within the group
and they must cultivate appropriate
relationship with other groups
and and that again speaks to to this
nested
architecture of group community
bioregion i personally think that we we
might have
gone down a sort of maladaptive detour
by adding in
superfluous um sociopolitical layer
called the nation state and i i
personally feel that that's
an anachronism that that we probably
will
do without in in 200 years time and
we i think we need a global governance
system that
enables subsidiarity down to by regions
and communities
um as as as the structure um
but i'm glad you used the word i'm glad
you used the word subsidiarity
which is a catholic concept uh
and uh federalism is another which is
nested
and and i think that um it's part of
cultural evolution that it
always builds upon what already exists
and so we have a
global village of nations um
uh right now we also have other entities
we have
obviously corporate entities we have
religious
entities these are the existing
intermediate scales of social
organization and uh
with that is the starting point and this
is something else which has happened
in the past since it's and it's it's
based so much on a
on a perspective it's a perspective
change that can be the
game uh
uh changer and once again it's not new
it's happened
in the past and to some extent
in the present it's for a nation for
example or a leader of a nation
to see themselves and their nation
as a solid citizen of the world
uh uh i have a conversation with um
as part of a series called
evolution complexity in the third way of
entrepreneurship if we could provide a
link
to uh this series of uh of conversations
that basically reviews
uh foreign policy of people like woodrow
wilson
who was a globalist i mean he was an
advocate of the united nations for
example i mean he was responsible for
the united states center in world war
one because not to be an isolationist
because
basically it's that enlightened form of
self-interest
where if you're for our own long-term
good we really have to
to be working towards the towards the
global good
now that is a form of nationalism it is
a form of patriotism
but it it it's a form that subordinates
itself
to a higher good
and then seeks to have a higher
reputation
towards that end and of course that
involves sanctions against nations that
don't do that and
and that whole protective uh basically
the core design principle is operating
at a
national scale so the point being is
that
our current organizations
governance structures of all kinds
uh can be part of the solution
as soon as they adopt that perspective
of subordinating themselves to
the higher global good and we see that
for example with the pope's
encyclical our common home speaks to the
whole earth not just to the catholic
faith we get the dollar llama
ethics for the whole world beyond
religion
and so it happens again and again that
that
that entities are are not narrowly
selfish they work for the common good
and it's there that to succeed they need
to apply
those same golden principles those same
principles that are needed at a small
scale
are needed at that large scale and the
same flexibility
you just recently had the opportunity to
have a
within the mind life institute series to
have a conversation with
with the dalai lama um right i'll link
that
also to with all like with this
conversation so people can have a look
at it
but is it so you mentioned
that subsidiarity is a catholic concept
i i
i'm aware of it as a political
philosophy that is written into the
european constitution and and that we
should actually be governed in this way
but i don't i'm not aware of the the
catholic past of this
term enlighten me well i'm not a scholar
on the topic but i believe
the concept originated uh in the uh
in the catholic faith and then and then
was borrowed by
in the formation of the european union
and basically the principle is is that
the lower level entities should be able
to
do things their way and the higher level
entities
such as the church should step in only
when
problems are caused higher up the scale
and that's also the
principle of federalism is that the
states and the
cities and the towns have a degree of
of authority to govern their affairs and
only one that causes problems higher up
the scale does something else kick
in so and then the european union
adopted those same uh
those same principles
but how do you sense like in in terms of
implementing
the eight design principles in a
scale-linking way from
small communities to bioregions to
basically
um a a global
collaborative network of groups humanity
trying to
keep the planet viable for
humanity to some extent and and the rest
of life
is the
current economic system not stacked
against that kind of system emerging so
like because you've done a lot of work
in
in economics as well and really look
looked into this and you helped
launch the evonomics
website and um what's what's your take
on to what extent we need a fundamental
redesign
of uh our economic system is it a
retrofit of capitalism
or is capitalism in and of itself the
very notion of
owning the means of production that that
then actually
sabotages a common pool resource because
suddenly
you don't have the principle which is a
[Music]
fair distribution of costs and benefits
don't really exist anymore
if you have land ownership and some sort
of retribution for i'll let you work my
land and therefore i don't really need
to do very much but you need to give me
something because i own the land
um where do you see the the need of this
which is also starting everywhere at the
moment with the we all alliance and
and lots of um not so alternative
20 years ago it was very alternative
groups who were trying to work on
alternative economic models
and and it was heresy to critique
um the the growth imperative
in in our current economic system now
this has changed completely and
everybody seems to and to be in
agreement that the current
economic system is is broken and driving
maladaptive behaviors sorry about the
[Music]
somebody's having an opinion on this um
so yeah i would love to hear you on on
how to bring these principles into a new
form of economic
um playing field that that actually
would us would enable us
to build that scale linking system
well um this this
enables me to describe this series of
conversations that i
already uh alluded to
evolution complexity and the third way
of entrepreneurship
let me briefly describe its thesis
and then some of the conversations
around which is an answer to your
to your uh question
uh so the thesis of the third way is
that there's two things that don't work
and only one thing that can work
one thing that doesn't work as ways i
fear because it's just
profoundly not the case that the pursuit
of lower level self-interest
robustly benefits the common good the
metaphor of the invisible hand
is profoundly untrue unless the
invisible hand is actually
our own systemic uh
efforts to construct an economy that
works at the systemic
uh scale the other thing that doesn't
work for centralized planning
because the world is too complex to be
planned by any group of
of uh experts and those of course are
the two major narratives of
of uh social
change so the only thing that can work
is a managed process of controlling
systemic goals in mind in other words we
must have a systemic target of selection
the welfare of the whole earth
ultimately or a sub-sub-system
uh there must be variation oriented
around the target and then there must be
the replication of best practices
realizing that they're sensitive to to
context now it's against that background
that that we can
appreciate both the areas of capitalism
and the
areas of socialism and one of the essays
one of the conversations is with jeffrey
hodgson who's a great
scholar of the social sciences in
england and he you know if you didn't
know before then you
really should know that every concerted
effort
at socialism has been a cataclysmic
failure
and they for true reasons one is is they
tried to do away with markets
altogether and to base their economy on
centralized planning that was problem
number one
problem number two was is that power got
concentrated in the hands of a few
elites
and we know how that always goes so even
for socialist movements that started out
well meaning
genuinely well-meaning and they
all of them became basically
totalitarian and
failed abysmally because of their
reliance on
centralized uh planning and if we want
some version of socialism we all have to
be clear
not that kind please then we have the
areas of capitalism that are
that are well known so what's in between
what are some examples
of the third way the third way is not
new because it's the only thing that can
work it's the only thing that ever has
worked and so we can see them
again and again described in all their
local vocabularies as i mentioned
mentioned before and it will come as no
surprise
that the nordic countries good old
norway denmark sweden
finland and einstein plus some other
nations
that are and all of the analyses books
such as why nations fail the spirit
level would
basically rank nations on how will they
function
at the national scale if you look at the
high end which always includes the
nordic countries plus others we don't
want to focus exclusively on
on the nordic countries and you find
that these are societies that
that uh work well and then come to
look closer as to why they work well
it's because they have actually created
a wonderful
balance their market economies make no
mistake they are
definitely market economies that are
competing
on the world stage but labor is also
strong
and the state is strong and they're all
working collaboratively
in order to improve the national
good and i was just i mean literally
two days ago i had my conversation
with some colleagues in norway on this
topic for that series and just to give
you a great illustration
there's something called the flex
security model
that was first developed in denmark and
is now
practiced widely also in in norway and
it goes this way
because these small nations are exposed
to the world economy
they have to be really nimble on the
market and so that means that any
particular
sector has to be able to hire and fire
workers
quite quickly you can't be stodgy that
way
um and so there has to be security for
workers but it can't be of the sort that
they just have job security and they
can't you know
then then the economy couldn't couldn't
need well so what they do is they
combine the ability to hire and fire
at will with a great social security
system so that if you lose your job
actually for a period of even four years
initially now it's been reduced to two
years
you could have continue on 90 of your
salary
until you can really train for the next
job
and so you combine social security
with a responsive
uh economy that's what they call flexi
flex security and it was worked out
basically by a collaborative
arrangement with the labor unions and
the
business sector with very strong state
uh state involvement so these go by
names such as
uh democratic socialism
uh and similar names which basically
combine the word socialism
that means that if everything is
explicitly designed for the good of the
society but also democratic
there's your participation so it's not
just in the hands of a few
elites and then that's represented by an
equality of power among the
major sectors such as labor and capital
and
and uh and uh and so on so
there's our model uh and uh
not hard to emulate every every nation
has to find its own path
there's more to be said about that but
uh anyhow there's
a there's a model to follow but but
don't you find like i i saw a talk that
you gave
um to the business business for peace
foundation
and and you kind of contrasted that
current economic orthodox economic
design is
i think what did you say um
has an absurd conception of human nature
has an absurd conception of
um economic systems equilibrium and has
an
um absurd conception of theory
um as nothingness and which i very much
like because it kind of resonates with
my
issue around qualitative and
quantitative um
for focuses or focus and then then you
say that
that the other option by building an
evolutionary er in
economics theory on multi-level
selection
um we can build it on the most current
knowledge about human nature
and social economic systems um in in all
of their complexity and the conception
that uh is commensurate with
evolutionary theory and
complexity the problem is that
it seems like both academically and
in terms of national policy making
economics has built this
this
wall of orthodoxy around it that it's
very difficult to actually
um have these conversations with with
about redesigning national
and international economic uh policies
are you making wrote there
yeah so i mean i've written extensively
on that including that particular talk
and it's absolutely the case that uh
everything that we know with the you
know gathered under the term homo
economics
is a huge part of the problem i talked
about paradigmatic change
earlier and so that's a paradigm that
actually only became dominant after
world war ii
was a fringe position before then but
then did become
truly dominant remains dominant and
has got to go basically it does have to
be replaced with a more holistic view
this represented by people such as k
rayworth and her donut
economics a systemic basically there's
your third way
a systemic goal
and and means towards working towards
that goal so the question becomes
you know i mean how fast are we going to
have that paradigm change
uh so that we really leave homo
economics
behind and then we adopt this more um
systemic approach and i've been now kind
of
beginning as a total outsider
uh 10 or 12 years ago have now become
more of an insider
and i see a lot of flexibility i mean
it's gotten to the point of collapse you
know close enough to the
point of collapse that uh people that
are very well
positioned inside the economic
establishment they get it
and they're really happy to to uh
to experiment so i do think that we've
reached the point
and it does take a collapse uh does take
a crisis
in order to move people beyond their
entrenched
uh uh positions but uh i think one thing
i'd like to do
daniel is to talk a little bit more
specifically about regenerative
movements
and to describe one that we're involved
with with pro-social
that i'd like to get your opinion on it
to see how closely it matches
some of the regenerative movements that
you're involved
um with and uh this one is called
forever green it's in uh based in
minnesota
and we're also working with a group
called regenerate illinois
and it's all about regenerative
agriculture which is if
if anything qualifies as a paradigm
shift gets to
transition from the current agricultural
practices in the american midwest
to a more regenerative
form of agriculture using for example
perennial crops
so that so that you're not just breaking
up the soil again
and again and to create a system which
is attuned to
uh everything from biodiversity to of
course management of the soil that turns
into water management
um and uh to be really holistic about
the system that you're trying to
create and as soon as you try to do that
then you realize that if you're gonna
for example
raise a new crop such as a perennial
wheat crop
then there has to be a whole supply
chain that you build
around it you just can't insert that one
practice you have to be working on the
whole supply
chain and so that is what and it should
be at the watershed
level if you're going to be ecologically
sound you have to respect you have to
start thinking about biological units
not just
units and so here we have like a number
of movements that are
like that and then the question is
how well do they work and how much
better might they work if
we begin to come in with a program such
as pro-social which is explicitly
evolutionary uh
not just in terms of the core design
principles but in terms of this flexor
flexibility but here's the thing we want
to do but how do we actually do it how
do we get them
unstuck and become flexible about
moving in uh at all scales from the
individual to the small group so on and
so on and so forth so this is just
starting and i feel lucky that we've
been invited to
to um to uh take part and it's the kind
of opportunity that we're looking for
uh elsewhere so i hope that
um that uh some of the projects that
you're involved in
then uh we could uh we could uh explore
collaborative potential
with you just as we are with that
particular project
i i would love that i mean you mentioned
kate rayworth
earlier like i'm because i i
feel a very strong personal need um like
i moved to mallorca
an island in the middle of the
mediterranean ten years ago
um not because well partially because i
like living in a mediterranean climate
and new york has a wonderful place to
live
and i'll admit that but i also moved
here because of the
the conviction that the locus of focus
for creating a viable
model of that change is possible not a
cookie cutter model
that then has to be implemented
everywhere else but but to show
that you can turn an entire bioregional
economy
around towards ecosystems restoration
and social and economic regeneration
away
from a heavily tourism-addicted
80 percent of the economy coming from
tourism
regional economy and and now with
covet 19 of course finally the the
tourism industry has
had that major disruption that i have
been
talking to them for 10 years about but
they always looked at me as the prophet
of doom
and and said we're earning more money
every year
um who is this guy telling us this isn't
our days are numbered
um and so there's a huge opportunity
right now um
to because of my my work
working with the kind of forefront of
the regenerative networks that have been
springing up all around the globe to
really invite
some of the best people in that field
to to work with the people of mallorca
and the uniqueness of this mallorcan
case study
to explore a turnaround
because the government is beginning to
be much more
willing to have those kind of
conversations and be inspired
and and one of the the ideas was i don't
know if you've seen that
that um the donut economics action lab
that
um kate founded last year has started to
work with
the biomimicry institute and they've
created funded by the c-40 network
the cities network they've created a
methodology called thriving places
um and and now kate's working with the
city of amsterdam
amsterdam has called itself a donut city
they've created the methodology of how
to
basically ground the donut social
foundations
and within ecological boundaries to to
ground it in um in cities and i've i've
always had this conversation with kate
that
ever since patrick getters we know um
who wrote a wonderful book called cities
and evolution which
if you know it you know what he was like
back in darwin's day he was the
father of our planning and and so
he he always said we a healthy city can
only be planned within
um its region and and so basically he
was one of the first bioregionalists
in academic terms um our species is a
bioregional species so
that like the pattern is is much older
but i i'm sure that
like as this is building with i'm also
working with
the um common land foundation the
lymphavedas work
um are you familiar with the four
returns
approach to ecosystems restoration uh
what's it called
four returns it's no i'm not one of
these parallel developments that i
i don't know about yet i'll send you a
link it's it's a little focused
on the entry point is ecosystems
restoration
but because willem favila used to be the
head of iucn netherlands and realized
that you can't
protect biodiversity hot spots if you
don't work with the
the regional economy and make it an
incentive
to want to protect it so it's like you
can't just
like if there's economic um
difficulty in an area they will impinge
on
protected biodiversity reserves and so
he's developed a very
agile language built around the four
returns the
return of inspiration the return of
ecological capital social capital
and eventually economic capital but what
what
is very unique about his approach is
that where they engage with
a region they only do so if there's a
commitment over 20 years so they
um calculate in that that the turnaround
of a of an ecological productive system
has to have the length of
change that the biological system needs
so if you if you want to go from a
heavily degraded
landscape to a much more bioproductive
landscape
it you can have massive effects within
the first three to six years but
but to really establish it it takes 20
years and
and so i'm i'm trying to currently
align the stars so to speak to work with
a number of institutions also the
capital institute's regenerative
economics approach to
use mallorca as a case study and and as
that matures
i would love to to involve you in that
though yeah well let me
let me uh this is so exciting because it
says grand coalescence which needs to to
uh to take place and so uh
here's the kind of my part of this
coalescing um and it illustrates some of
the points we've been made
uh before so um only two years ago
i attended a workshop
in uh in uh
seattle uh organized by a foundation
that was basically a liberal progressive
foundation they wanted to
go beyond the neoliberal model they
wanted actually they admired the
montpellier society
which was the organization that actually
established the neoliberal model and
they said
we'd like to repeat that act for a more
progressive
way of doing things there and that an
economist named dennis snower who i did
not know about before
but he's very important man he was the
president of the keel institute for
world economics
which organizes the t20 and
g20 summit meetings so this is basically
a world
international economist and damned if he
wasn't a convert to multi-level
selection theory he'd already read about
this
stuff and he was persuaded he was
persuaded so i started to work with
diana's
um and he invited me to the t27 meetings
and he started to talk about himself in
his own talk so
that's what i said you know the
basically the orthodoxy the insiders the
established economists are actually uh
being
persuaded it's not it's becoming less uh
heterodox and uh he's also involved in
the uk
and so he was helpful in me getting a
grant from the
economic and social science research
council which was one of the main
foundations in the in the uk and they
have a whole
program within the esrc called
rebuilding macroeconomics so here again
basically we have soul searching within
the uh establishment
so i got a actually quite a small grant
to work with denison to implement
pro-social and here's what we did
we organized a training course and that
training course was made available to
small teams representing organizations
and this is quite important because this
course actually
was a four-tier population structure
within the course the students in the
course were of course individuals that's
tier one
there were also memories of small teams
that's tier two
those teams represented organizations
which i'll shortly list that's
tier three and those organizations were
interacting with each other through the
teams
there's tier four so what were these
organizations
well it included kate rayworth and diehl
and she brought in circle economy which
was organized in the
she also brought in c40 which you've
just
mentioned plus a community group called
civic square which is based in
birmingham we'll go down to the to the
community
level we brought in the rsa the royal
society for arts and manufactures which
has
over 20 000 followers and it's
uh thanks an organization called the
banking standards board which is a very
interesting organization that formed
after
uh 2008 to help improve the reputation
of the
british banking uh
industry uh with the transition network
the transition time network was
a team all of them were taking this and
learning about pro-social in relation to
their own organizations which of course
were already very dynamic and do you
know they saw a lot of added
value complementarity basically not
competitors it's just
like oh we already do this that's not
what happened what happened was in a
real
synergy in terms of these organizations
that are already are doing
you know driving towards exactly the
right thing turns out that actually to
think about it more explicitly about
managing
the cultural evolutionary process
according to evolutionary and complex
systems fundamentals
was a considerable added
value and so now we're at the point
where we have a great working
relationship with kate and
these other organizations that we can
actually work together so
any legion that wants to become a donut
economics region such as amsterdam or
any place else including smaller scales
by all means because that's definitely
the systemic approach that we're working
towards
but in order to do that then i
won't quite promise you because that
would be too much hubris
but i'm confident that uh
in an effort to do that if we work at
the scale of small groups and then we
implement
a social then they will go better so um
and it is inherently conclusive i mean
those core design principles are
fundamentally democratic and called for
for co-production participatory
action all those good things in which
basically the group
starting at the scale of smaller groups
it genuinely consults them
as to the role that they want for
themselves what's meaningful
for them and how to achieve it in the
context
of the greater the greater uh good
so this makes me optimistic that uh
that we could really catalyze the
process of cultural evolution
by this coalescing that's taking place
yeah
my senses i mean if you haven't had a
chance to talk to
michael uh bowens and his team from the
peer to peer foundation
i would be very happy to make an
introduction and i feel like the two of
you would
would have also a lot of
overlap and synergy to discover um
my my senses how do we
like i i'm definitely committed to
working on
using mallorca as a place that convenes
collaborations around this and initially
it's a sort of using majorca with the
locals as an example to have a concrete
place
where to apply these these ideas and
bring together
some of the input of deal and and
capital institute and common land
into it into a structure that that that
creates
synergies between these different
approaches um
but there's this this this concern
with regard to redesigning economics
that i also wanted to briefly address
before we wrap up because we've already
talked
a long time um
i've noticed that in a lot of the
attempts to create an approach to
regenerative economics there's
there's on the one hand there's kate's
wonderful work there's
um john fullerton's eight principles
um there also a lot of people who are
trying to
create mechanisms by which the very
process
of changing the state of a degraded
landscape
from a degenerate generated
not very productive eroding landscape
towards a
increasingly productive and healthier
landscape
they want to include that somehow into
the economic balance sheets
to with the best of intentions in the in
the sense that farmers
can then be paid twice not just for the
produce that they regeneratively harvest
off their land but
also for the very process of
regenerating for fixing carbon into soil
for
improving healthy ecosystems functions
and similarly there are models that are
trying to
do that with social regeneration
the danger and i would love to have have
your perspective on this
of working with this multi-capital
framework within a new type of economic
system
where it's not just financial capital
but you have social capital and
ecological capital and so on and so
forth
for me i've always seen a big danger
that it opens the back door
for only one little because because of
the mathiness of
economic theory only one little maths
function that
converts financial capital or converts
social capital or ecological capital or
any of the other capitals
into financial capital can then be the
backdoor
to commoditizing all
human relationships and all health
relationships within a healthy complex
ecosystem
and and so with the best of
intention-created
methods actually become complicit
in the largest form of enclosure of the
commons
that has has happened yet um i'm i'm a
little bit nervous about that because at
the same time i see the need
to value social capital and ecological
capital within
economic balance sheets in a different
way have you
got an opinion on on that issue i think
that descends into a level of detail
of implementation that uh
i'm no authority on uh and so
and in some sense i don't have a comment
on it specifically
uh because it's just gonna have to be uh
worked out i mean basically it's like
should we do it this way what are the
dangers of doing it this way as opposed
to doing it
um uh that way and that reveals a very
important point that ostrom eleanor made
again and again distinguishing between
a functional design principle and its
implementation
and so for a group to work well it needs
to
implement these design principles in a
functional sense but how they do so
is highly contingent on the
context so every group needs to monitor
but how they monitor depends on
the context and so on for all of the
design uh principles and here i think
we're getting into
contextual issues of implementation in
which but one thing we're going to have
to do for sure
when we assess our practices is to be
holistic about it and to
and to look at you know one of the what
are the systemic consequences
of of doing it this way versus uh
uh versus uh um
that way so i think that um
uh we do want to to uh
wrap up and i i want to give a sense of
just
how this uh uh
[Music]
can can work i'm glad that you mentioned
multiple forms of capital because it
means that if you're in a situation
where there's not much financial capital
but there's other forms of capital then
it's possible to
implement prosocial simply because
there's a strong
appetite for doing so so for example if
you had any groups that you're working
with
there any groups at all that were
really excited about giving prosocial
a world i'll find facilitators for you
and it can be done online
uh so that uh so that we can get going
no charge
um of course if you do have something
you know any kind of resources or a
foundation like the peer-to-peer
foundation or any
other foundation would like to
facilitate it
and incentivize it so that people
actually have financial capital and
in addition to their other forms of
capital well of course it'll go better
as long as we use those funds in the
right in the right way but we don't have
to wait for the money
yeah in order to uh in order to do this
there does have to be of course
enthusiasm for doing it people
have to be willing to need and act
on the basis of what they what they
decide there has to be
some form of of uh
of of capital but uh uh so
uh uh we're we're structuring pro-social
obviously to sustain itself
so it has to have a financial model but
to sustain itself in a way that it could
offer
uh offer itself uh for free
basically when
when uh when necessary the epsrc work
you mentioned earlier
is there a report that i could share
with people locally is
or is that too reason to have been
written up yet oh there's
lots of stuff and i'm happy to to be
present and
and other people to talk about
possibilities there's a lot that i can
share
um about that if you wanted to approach
groups and uh
then we'll talk about that offline great
well this this has been rich and and
opening up a very hopeful window towards
future conversations and future
collaborations so this
it's it's a real yeah thank you so much
for the last two hours
can't believe we almost well um okay
thank you so much for your time and and
i'll i'll be in touch soon and
um and look forward to meeting you in
person hopefully and not
too distant future okay maybe on a
mediterranean island somewhere
yeah that's that's the little carrot
i've got here it's a good location
people like to work with mallorca as a
case study because
it's a good excuse to come here for a
research too
great have a wonderful rest of the day
and thank you so much i'll um
probably take me maybe a week or two
to upload this but i'll send you the
link um once it's upgraded
great great bye